Okay בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*. Today's דף daf.
*daf* is פ"ט *Peh-Tet*, 89, and we pick up at the bottom
of פ"ח עמוד ב' *Peh-Chet Amud Bet* and in the middle of
אגדתא aggadeta. *Aggadatas* relating to מתן תורה Matan Torah *Matan Torah*. So
it's the two dots, it's about eight lines before or about 12
lines from the bottom. דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi, *De-amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi*, said רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi
Yehoshua Ben Levi *Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi*, בשעה שעלה משה למרום b'shaa
she-ala Moshe l'marom, *be-sha'ah she-alah Moshe la-marom*, when משה Moshe *Moshe* went
on high, when to receive the תורה Torah *Torah*, אמרו מלאכי השרת
Malakhei HaShareis, לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא Hakadosh Baruch Hu, *amru malachei ha-sharet
lifnei Ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu*, so the heavenly angels said to God, ריבונו
של עולם *Ribbono Shel Olam*, Master of the Universe, מה לילוד אשה
בינינו *mah le-yilud ishah beineinu*, what is this person born of woman
doing amongst us? What is this mortal man doing up here? Yes.
אמר להם Amar lahem *Amar lahem*, He said to them, לקבל תורה
Torah בא *lekabbel Torah ba*, he's coming to receive the תורה Torah
*Torah*. אמרו לפניו *Amru lefanav*, so they said to Him, חמודה גנוזה
שגנוזה לך תשע מאות שבעים וארבעה דורות קודם שנברא העולם *hamudah genuzah
she-genuzah le-cha t'sha me'ot shivim ve-arba'ah dorot kodem she-nivra ha-olam*, this very
desirous treasured hidden object that was hidden for You
974 generations before the world was created, אתה מבקש ליתנה לבשר ודם
*atah mevakesh litnah le-basar va-dam*? You want to give it to flesh
and bones
or to flesh and blood? מה אנוש כי תזכרנו ובן אדם כי
תפקדנו *Mah enosh ki tizkerennu u-ven adam ki tifkedennu*? So what is
a person that You should remember him or that You should pay
attention to him and a human being that You should notice him?
ה' אדונינו מה אדיר שמך בכל הארץ אשר תנה הודך על השמים
*Hashem Adoneinu mah addir shimcha be-chol ha-aretz asher tenah hodecha al ha-shamayim*.
ה' *Hashem* our God, how great is Your name in the whole
land, Your glory should be given up in heaven. Keep Your glory,
keep the תורה Torah *Torah* which is Your glory in heaven, there's
enough of Your glory down on the earth, מה אדיר שמך בכל
הארץ *mah addir shimcha be-chol ha-aretz*, but Your true glorious thing, the
תורה Torah *Torah*, should be kept up in heaven. Now the 974
is because the generation that received the תורה Torah, *Torah* is the
26th generation, right? 10 generations from אדם *Adam* until נח Noach. *Noach*,
10 from נח *Noach* until אברהם Avraham? *Avraham*, then you have אברהם
Avraham, *Avraham*, יצחק Yitzchak? *Yitzchak*, יעקב Yaakov? *Yaakov*, let's see how this
works out, יעקב Yaakov *Yaakov*, לוי *Levi*, עמרם *Amram*, משה Moshe *Moshe*.
There you go. So alright. So anyway, so the idea that the
תורה Torah. *Torah* was given after a thousand generations, so there were
976 that were created beforehand. Now obviously also what this
is setting up is that the תורה Torah *Torah* is not just
or is this thing that was preceded בריאת העולם berias ha'olam, *beri'at
ha-olam*, it is some it is something that is not just instructions
for how people are supposed to live their lives. It doesn't just,
obviously that's going to be משה Moshe *Moshe*'s response as we see
that element of it, but the whole way this is sort of
setting it up is that this is something which ultimately belongs in
the divine realms. It's not fundamentally made for human beings and it
preceded the whole creation of the world. So let's see what משה
Moshe *Moshe* responds. So אמר לו amar lo, הקדוש ברוך הוא *amar
lo Ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu*, so God said to משה Moshe *Moshe*, החזר
להם תשובה teshuvah, *hachzer lahem teshuvah*, go give them a response. אמר
לפניו Amar lefanav, *Amar lefanav*, so משה Moshe *Moshe* said to Him,
said in front of God's presence, ריבונו של עולם *Ribbono Shel Olam*,
Master of the Universe, מתירא אני שמא ישרפוני בהבל שבפיהם *mityarei ani
shema yisrefuni be-hevel she-befihem*, I am afraid that they will burn me
up with the breath in their mouth. I how can I argue
with angels? אמר לו Amar lo, *Amar lo*, He said to him,
אחוז בכסא כבודי *achoz be-chisse kevodi*, hold on to the throne of
My glory והחזר להם תשובה teshuvah. *ve-hachzer lahem teshuvah* and give them
a response, שנאמר she'ne'emar מאחז פני כסא פרשז עליו עננו *she-ne'emar me'achez
penei kisse parshaz alav anano*.
Holding on to the presence of the throne, פרשז *parshaz* on him
His cloud. So what does פרשז *parshaz* mean? ואמר רב תנחום ואמר
רב נחמן בר תנחום *ve-amar Rav Tanchum ve-amar Rav Nachman bar Tanchum*,
מלמד שפירש שדי מזיו שכינתו *melammed she-pireish Shaddai mi-ziv shechinato*. So פרשז
*parshaz* is פירש שדי זיו *pireish Shaddai ziv*,
that God spread over משה Moshe *Moshe* the shining of God's presence
ועננו עליו *ve-anano alav* and clouded over him, protected him so that
משה Moshe, *Moshe* could respond to the heavenly angels. So here's משה
Moshe, *Moshe*'s response. אמר לפניו Amar l'fanav, *Amar lefanav*, so משה Moshe
*Moshe* said to God, ריבונו של עולם *Ribbono Shel Olam*, Master of
the Universe, תורה Torah שאתה נותן לי מה כתיב בה *Torah she-atah
noten li mah ketiv bah*? This תורה Torah *Torah* that You are
giving to me or planning to give to me, giving to me,
what's written in it?
אנכי ה' אלוהיך אשר הוצאתיך מארץ מצרים Mitzrayim *Anochi Hashem Elohecha
asher hotzeiticha me-eretz Mitzrayim*.
So presumably either it was rhetorical and משה Moshe *Moshe* said that
or that was God's response, but sounds like משה Moshe *Moshe* saying
that. Anyway, I am ה' *Hashem* your God that have taken you
out of the land of Egypt. אמר להם *Amar lahem*, so he
said to the angels, למצרים ירדתם *Le-Mitzrayim yeradetem*? Let me get this
straight. Did you go down to Egypt? לפרעה השתעבדתם *Le-Pharaoh hishtabbadetem*?
Did you subject yourselves, were you enslaved to פרעה *Pharaoh*? So תורה
Torah, למה תהא לכם *Torah lamah te-hei lachem*? Why should the תורה
Torah, *Torah* be for you? It doesn't refer to you, it refers
to us, refers to things that happened to human beings. שוב מה
כתיב בה shuv mah ksiv bah? *Shuv mah ketiv bah*? What else
is written in it? לא יהיה לך
*Lo yiheyeh lecha*. בין עמים אתם
שרויין? Maybe you're living amongst foreign nations שעובדים עבודת גילולים she'ovdim avodas
gilulim
that they worship idols, and therefore you need to be told not
to worship idols? Top of פ"ט ע"א. Peh-Tet Amud Aleph. שוב מה
כתיב בה? shuv mah ksiv bah? What else is written in it?
זכור את יום השבת לקדשו, Zachor es yom haShabbos l'kadsho, remember the
Shabbos day to keep it holy. כלום אתם עושים מלאכה שאתם צריכים
שבות? klum atem osim melacha she'atem tzerichim shvus?
Do you work during the rest of the week that you need
to rest on Shabbos? שוב מה כתיב בה? shuv mah ksiv bah?
What else is written in it? לא תשא, Lo sisa, do not,
do not take God's name in vain. משא ומתן יש
ביניכם? masa u'matan yeish beineichem? It's an interesting play on תשא tisa
and משא ומתן, masa u'matan, but basically also why would somebody swear
in God's name in vain in order to cheat in business? Perhaps
you're doing business that you have to be told not to swear
on God's name in vain? שוב מה כתיב בה? shuv mah ksiv
bah? What else is written in it? כבד את אביך ואת אמך,
Kabeid es avicha v'es imecha, honor your father and mother. אב ואם
יש לכם? av v'eim yeish lachem? Do you have mother and father?
שוב מה כתיב בה? לא תרצח, Lo sirtzach, לא תנאף, lo sinaf,
לא תגנוב. lo signov. Don't, don't kill, don't commit adultery, don't, don't
burgle. קנאה יש בכם, kinah yeish bachem, יצר הרע יש ביניכם? yeitzer
hara yeish beineichem? Do you have jealousy which presumably is what leads
to many of these things? Do you have, do you have an
evil inclination? So none of this is relevant to you. מיד הודו
לו להקדוש ברוך הוא miyad hodu lo l'Hakadosh Baruch Hu and immediately
all the angels agreed to God. Interesting, they didn't agree to Moshe.
Okay, Moshe though made the point and they agreed to God that
God was right to want to give it to people. שנאמר ה'
אדונינו מה אדיר שמך בכל הארץ. she'ne'emar Hashem Adoneinu mah adir shimcha
b'chol ha'aretz. So that's the פסוק pasuk that follows right? This is
all from the same פרק perek in תהלים. Tehillim. ואילו תנה הודך
על השמים לא כתיב. v'ilu tnah hodecha al hashamayim lo ksiv.
But the second time it's written it doesn't say "give your glory
to heaven" because by the second time they said fine, put it
on the earth, it doesn't, it should not stay you know, it
should not stay bound up in heaven.
מיד הודו לו להקדוש ברוך הוא. miyad hodu lo l'Hakadosh Baruch Hu.
Moshe also addresses הקדוש ברוך הוא, not the angels.
Right, that's a good point too. אמר לפניו רבונו של עולם. amar
lefanav Ribbono Shel Olam. No, but then when he says כלום klum
he asks God what's written in it but then when he says
למצרים ירדתם לפרעה השתעבדתם, l'Mitzrayim yaradtem l'Pharaoh hishtabtem, right, he is talking
to them. Maybe he's talking to them via, right? Okay, but that
is true. So to what degree have they directly, are they directly
interacting?
Address the speaker of the house you know.
Right, that's a good point. Right, right.
And Moshe would have known all this before the Torah was given?
Well that's why he said "God, what's written in it?" Maybe he
just trusted that whatever God would say he would have a way
to prove his point. Okay,
well let's finish the point and then we can talk a little
more about it. Okay. So מיד miyad immediately כל אחד ואחד נעשה
לו אוהב.
kol echad v'eichad na'asah
lo oheiv.
Every one of these heavenly angels became you know, a dear friend
to Moshe. ומסר לו דבר u'masar lo davar and gave him some,
and gave him something or some like secret, you know, we'll see.
שנאמר she'ne'emar as it says עלית למרום שבית שבי לקחת מתנות באדם.
alisa lamarom shavisa shevi lakachta matanos ba'adam. You've gone up to high,
you have taken you know, you have taken booty,
you have taken gifts of people. What does that mean? בשכר שקראוך
אדם. bishchar shekrucha adam.
They were sort of demeaning you and calling you like בשר ודם,
basar vadam, you know, מה אנוש בן אדם כי תפקדנו, mah enosh
ben adam ki sifkedenu,
this is just a person, why do you give him any recognition?
And you know, so you had to suffer through that. So in
that reward so, where was I? בשכר שקראוך אדם לקחת מתנות. bishchar
shekrucha adam lakachta matanos.
You got gifts from them. What were those gifts? So we'll see
a sense of it in a minute. אף מלאך המות מסר לו
דבר. af Malach HaMaves masar lo davar. Even the angel of death
gave Moshe a secret gift. שנאמר Shenemar, as it says ויתן את
הקטרת ויכפר על העם. vayiten es haktoret vayichaper al ha'am.
This was Aharon but Moshe basically sent him to do it when
the plague broke out, the מגיפה. mageifah. So Moshe sent Aharon and
he put the incense and it atoned for the people and the
מגיפה mageifah ceased and the people stopped dying. Right? ואומר ויעמד בין
המתים ובין החיים ותעצר המגפה. v'omer vaya'amod bein hametim uvein hachayim vate'atzar
hamageifah. He's
Aharon stood between the dead and the living and the מגיפה, mageifah,
the plague ceased. So how did he know that the קטרת ktoret
would do that? So אי לאו דאמר ליה, i lav d'amar leh,
if it had not been that the angel of death had told
him that the way you stop a מגיפה mageifah is by the
burning of קטרת, ktoret, מי הוה ידע, mi hava yada, how would
he have known? It must be that he had this secret from
this event. So it's quite a fascinating מדרש midrash about you know
first of all, I have to, that number one the idea that
Moshe has to argue to get it to come down you know
just so much underscores these other ideas that we have about the
Torah about the you know Torah that preceded בריאת העולם, this sense
of like you know that it's not just a communication of God
to people how they're supposed to live their lives but it ultimately
is you know the eternal truth and to some degree you know
maybe it doesn't even belong you know something that is so spiritual
doesn't even belong down here in a physical world. So you know
the angel arguing and Moshe has to point out but it also
has these other, these other elements to it which make it, which
make it relevant to us and which very much do make it
our Torah as well. So it's a nice way I think of
encapsulating you know both of those ideas, obviously the fact that it
is directed to how we live our lives but also this supernal
nature to it. I just want to point out two other points
and then I'll take questions. One other thing to point out is
that the מהרש"א Maharsha points out is... the same פסוקים pesukim. *Pesukim*
used מה אנוש כי תזכרנו *Mah Enosh Ki Tizkerennu* are used in
another מדרש Midrash. *Midrash* to talk about the angels wanting to resist
when God wanted to create human beings. Why do you want to
create human beings? I mean, you know, they're בשר ודם *Basar V'dam*,
what value do they have and so on. So it's interesting, you
know, because first of all, it's just the same theme, you know,
the angels saying, you know, what good, you know, you should pay
all of your attention up here, why are you paying attention to
anything down there? But also could it be understood as also to
some degree like a partial response, you know, that the value of
creating humans is the ability of humans to strive for, you know,
for the divine and the giving of the תורה Torah *Torah* is
like the end of that process. You know, you could devalue everything,
you know, why give, why create them, why give them the תורה
Torah, *Torah*? But no, the whole point is is that you create
something that is, you know, both has, you know, as it were,
a spiritual component and a physical component and you give them the
תורה Torah *Torah* as a way of, you know, of actualizing their
spiritual component, which also by the way, I think the מהרש"א *Maharsha*
says, I think it's the מהרש"א *Maharsha* who says that the idea
of משה Moshe *Moshe* holding onto the כיסא *Kise* is basically saying
that what entitles us to receive the תורה Torah? *Torah* is that
we can reach for the divine. If we were all purely physical,
then the angels would be right, right? Why does בשר ודם *Basar
V'dam* get the תורה Torah? *Torah*? But the fact that God says,
what is allowing you to respond to the angels is you're holding
onto the כיסא *Kise*, the fact that we can reach towards the
divine and try to actualize the divine within us, you know, that
is what allows us, that's what entitles us to have the תורה
Torah *Torah* because that's also the role of the תורה Torah *Torah*
is for us to, you know, to actualize the divine within us.
The final point that I'll make about this is the idea of
like עלית למרום שבית שבי *Alita Lamarom Shavita Shevi*, you know, to
me, is evocative, I don't know if this was intended, but you
know, about the whole myth of Prometheus, you know, going up to,
you know, to steal the fire from the gods. And there the
idea is, you know, that sort of the sense of like human
creativity and so on and the gods didn't want, you know, human
beings to have it. Interestingly, many people are not aware that the
reason we do the בורא מאורי האש *Borei Meorei Ha-eish* in הבדלה
*Havdalah* מוצאי שבת Shabbat. *Motza'ei Shabbat* is not just because, well, you
couldn't have light candles on שבת *Shabbat*, you light it מוצאי שבת
*Motza'ei Shabbat* to show that it's the weekday, but also because the
מדרש Midrash *Midrash* says that the first after human beings were created,
after שבת *Shabbat*, so, you know, human beings were given the mandate,
you know, פרו ורבו וכבשוה *Pru U'rvu V'khivshuha* and their first act
of creativity of actually, you know,
sort
of subduing the world or taking control over the world was the
creation of fire. And it emphasizes the human creativity in the creation
of fire was like the first act and therefore the first act
of the week is like during the week is when we're supposed
to bring our creativity into the world. So that actually, you know,
that's not, that's seen as all human creation. But here the idea
of, you know, taking the תורה Torah *Torah* down from God where
there's this resistance, but again, it's the angels who are resisting, it's
God who wants to give it. So I don't know exactly what
to do with that, but to me certainly this idea of going
up and taking something that was trying to be held back from
up high, you know, certainly evokes to me somewhat of this myth.
So some points. Yes, Charlie, go ahead.
Well this is a big argument against the prevailing beliefs even in
the non-explicitly idol-worshiping religions because we're
saying that neither God nor spiritual creations such as angels have free
will, have the will to rebel.
I don't know whether we're saying that about God, but we're saying
it about angels, right. Certainly the whole idea of angels is that
they are complete just, you know, doing the will of God and
they don't make choices, they don't have free will. Now משה Moshe
*Moshe* never said that to that extreme. He didn't say you have
no choice, you don't need מצוות mitzvot *Mitzvot*. He sort of said
you don't have these realities or these temptations, but it is true
in general, you know, that there seems to be, whether it's absolute,
but definitely that strand that there's like basically no free will among
angels, right.
As opposed to say Zoroastrianism where you've got a negative being who's
almost on a par or Christianity with its free will angels.
Right, right, that's definitely true. That's definitely true. Yeah, רבקה Rivka. *Rivka*.
I wanted to, in the מדרש Midrash. *Midrash* that
said כפה עליהם הר כגיגית *Kafa Aleihem Har Ke-gigit*, because he's talking
about how the תורה Torah? *Torah* predated creation of the world. And
I know to me there's some contradiction because on the one hand
משה Moshe, *Moshe* is saying to the angels you don't need it,
you know, what, you have no use for the תורה Torah. *Torah*.
If so, why was it, you know, who was it there for?
Well, I think that's exactly the point. I think like many of
the מדרשים Midrashim, *Midrashim* that we've been reading until now, like the
כפה עליהם הר כגיגית *Kafa Aleihem Har Ke-gigit* and then also the
free will and the ברית *Berit* or whatever, it's trying to encapsulate
these like dialectics, you know, these like contradictions. So on the one
hand it's not just that the תורה Torah. *Torah* is an instruction
manual for people, right, we're not, you know, the תורה Torah. *Torah*
have to have this supernal, absolute divine truth idea element to it,
which is the whole... idea or that it, you know, it preceded
בריאת עולם and all of that. So that's encapsulated by what the
angels are saying and by what that it preceded like who needs
to give it to the people? This is some eternal divine truth.
And then
Moshe is talking about, yes, our Torah, the history, the whole בראשית,
Bereshit, it seems like it was unnecessary before, but then after
Abraham... Right.
Look, I mean, but you know, you know the
famous מדרשים, midrashim. right? Like הסתכל באורייתא וברא
עלמא, istakel be'Oraita uvara alma, that the Torah, God looked into the
Torah and created the world. So the fact that the תורה Torah
said that, you know, we were going to be slaves in Egypt
and all this, that was some type of this eternal truth that
then created the reality and not the reality and not in response
to it, you know? Or something, alright, we'll read the רש"י, Rashi,
but like the fact that, you know, לוט Lot is baking מצות,
matzot, right? They often quote that, right? Because it was פסח. Pesach.
So he's baking מצות matzot זכר ליציאת מצרים zecher l'Yitziat Mitzrayim even
though יציאת מצרים Yitziat Mitzrayim hadn't happened.
But I'm saying this, this is a true sort of strand, very
strong strand which is, is that, you know, is that it's not
like the תורה Torah. is just a response to physical material mundane,
you know, historical realities. There's an ultimate eternal truth to it to
some degree which creates those realities, not only responds to it. So
I think that's trying to encapsulate both of those ideas within this
מדרש.
Midrash And the fact that the angels don't want it to be
given... Yes. So on their part, some desires, they had
what
that represents that this is on one hand this is a spiritual
thing, so how can it be manifested in a physical way? On
the other hand Moshe is saying but this is a physical, you
know, it says words in it, you know, that tells us what
to actually do. Right. So but if the angels were just,
you know...
Yeah, I think this
is God's will.
Yes, but the giving here to give an expression to... Alright, we're
here, don't give it to them. Yeah, I understand. Look, this is
all, this is all as a way of expressing, you know, it's
a story that gives expression to these competing truths about how we
think about how we think about what תורה Torah. is. So you
want to read the רש"י? Rashi? He says, okay, תתקע"ד, tav tav
kuf ayin dalet,
so רש"י Rashi says, באותן תשע מאות ושבעים וארבע דורות שקדמו תורה
לעולם. b'otan tsha me'ot v'shivim v'arba dorot shekadmu Torah l'olam. So I
don't know how you fit in 974 generations in 2,000 years, but
anyway, that the תורה Torah preceded the world. היו עתידין דורות הללו
להבראות, hayu atidin dorot halalu l'hibra'ot,
these 974 generations should have been created, שנאמר דבר צוה לאלף דור,
shenemar davar tziva l'elef dor, that there were thousand generations that should
have existed before the תורה Torah. was given. וראה הקדוש ברוך הוא
שאין העולם מתקיים בלא תורה כל כך והעבירן ולא בראן, v'ra'a Hakadosh
Baruch Hu she'ein ha'olam mitkayem belo Torah kol kach v'he'eviran v'lo bra'an,
that the world can't exist for a thousand generations before getting the
תורה, Torah, והעבירן ולא בראן, v'he'eviran v'lo bra'an,
so he decided forget it, we're going to drop off 974 generations,
I won't, I won't, I'll create the world so early to give
there to be a period of a thousand generations to create, I'll
just create the world 26 generations before the giving of the תורה.
Torah, ונתנה לכ"ו דורות. un'tanah l'kaf vav dorot. Okay.
So what if he created the world 26...
God should have created the world so that there were thousand generations
before the תורה Torah, was given. But God realized that the world
wouldn't exist that long, you know, we would all like wind up
killing ourselves and it would just go back to תהו ובוהו. tohu
vavohu. So God had to say I have to create a much
shorter pre-history to the time of the giving of the תורה because
there can't be too many generations without the תורה we'll all fall
apart. Okay. That's what the generations of נח.
What? Felt like how we...
Well right, exactly, exactly.
So there's a מדרש midrash in בראשית רבה,
Bereshit Rabbah, what happened to those generations that were unborn? Right. They
were meant to exist. Right.
They're
distributed in
each generation.
Right. Okay, so let's now continue now, middle of פ"ב עמוד א,
peh bet amud aleph, the two dots.
I should also say by the way, it is interesting that, you
know, again, the emphasis of Moshe's response is about the מצוות mitzvot,
of the תורה, not about the narrative of the תורה, which is
also interesting thinking about, you know,
you know, sort of how we focus on what is the תורה
and what is the emphasis of it. Okay. ואמר רבי יהושע בן
לוי, v'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, and similarly said רבי יהושע בן
לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Levi he was the one that said the
previous whole
מדרש. midrash בשעה שירד משה מלפני הקדוש ברוך הוא, b'sha'ah sheyarad Moshe
milifnei Hakadosh Baruch Hu, when Moshe went down from God, he got
the תורה, he won that battle with the angels, בא שטן ואמר
לפניו, ba Satan v'amar lefanav, then the angel came and said to
him, רבונו של עולם, Ribono shel Olam, Master of the Universe, תורה
היכן היא, Torah heichan hi, where'd the תורה go?
So God... so so somehow שטן Satan missed the conversation. תוספות Tosafot
brings a מדרש midrash that God had distracted the שטן Satan with
some other thing, sent him out to go get a quart of
milk or something. So anyway he came back, he said what happened
to the תורה? אמר לו, Amar lo now which is by the
way fascinating the idea also which is just because it's taken down
doesn't it mean that it's taken away from heaven? You know, like
can't it be up in heaven and given to us? לא בשמים
היא, lo bashamayim hi, well that's true, I mean, but again that
idea that somehow now that it's ours, it's not just we also
have it, somehow it's less present in heaven. I think you're right,
it does relate to that לא בשמים היא. lo bashamayim hi. So
what happened to the תורה? אמר לו, Amar lo,
נתתיה לארץ, Netatiha la'aretz, I gave it to the earth. הלך, Halakh,
so maybe he meant that metaphorically to the people, but he took
it, the Satan took it literally, so הלך אצל ארץ. Halakh etzel
aretz. He went to the land. אמר לה, Amar lah, תורה היכן
היא, Torah heikhan hi, where's the Torah? אמרה לו, Amrah lo, so
the land said to him,
אלהים הבין דרכה והוא ידע את מקומה, Elohim hevin darkah vehu yada
et mekomah, that's at the end of the פסוק, pasuk, God knows
its path. So God knows, how do I know where the Torah
is? So הלך אצל ים, Halakh etzel yam, so he went to
the ocean and אמר לו Amar lo, and the ocean said to
the Satan, אין עמדי, Ein imadi, this is all from, this is
all, we'll see, it's all quoting a פסוק pasuk from איוב. Iyov.
הלך אצל תהום, Halakh etzel tehom, he went to the depths, אמר
לו, Amar lo, it said to the Satan, אין בי, Ein bi,
I don't have it, שנאמר, Shenemar, תהום אמר לא בי
היא והים אמר אין עמדי. Tehom amar lo bi hi vehayam amar
ein imadi. So the depths said I don't have it and the
ocean said it's not with me. אבדון ומות אמרו באזנינו שמענו שמעה,
Avaddon vamavet amru be'ozneinu shamanu shimah, but the sort of destruction and
death have said in our ears we have heard its report. So
the גמרא Gemara doesn't actually do anything with the אבדון ומות, Avaddon
vamavet, interestingly. חזר ואמר לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא, Hazar ve'amar lifnei Hakadosh
Barukh Hu, so the Satan came back and said to God, רבונו
של עולם, Ribbono Shel Olam, master of the universe, חיפשתי בכל הארץ
ולא מצאתיה, Hipasti bekhol ha'aretz velo metatiha, I looked throughout the entire
land, you know, the land, the ocean, the depths, I can't find
it. אמר לו, Amar lo, לך אצל בן עמרם, Lekh etzel Ben
Amram, maybe you want to go go talk to the son of
Amram. Okay now בן עמרם Ben Amram obviously emphasizes like the human
nature, ילוד אשה, Yelud ishah, right, born of woman. So go to
בן עמרם. Ben Amram. הלך אצל משה, Halakh etzel Moshe, he went
to Moshe, also downplays the importance of Moshe, like just a normal
person. He went to Moshe. אמר לו, Amar lo, so the Satan
said to him, תורה שנתן לך הקדוש ברוך הוא היכן היא, Torah
shenatan lekha Hakadosh Barukh Hu heikhan hi, the Torah that God has
given to you, where is it? אמר לו, so Moshe said back
to him, וכי מה אני שנתן לי הקדוש ברוך הוא תורה, Vekhi
mah ani shenatan li Hakadosh Barukh Hu Torah, who am I that
God should have given me the Torah? He didn't say he didn't
have it, notice. אמר ליה הקדוש ברוך הוא למשה, Amar lei Hakadosh
Barukh Hu le-Moshe, so God said to Moshe, משה בדאי אתה, Moshe
badai attah, Moshe what, you're a liar? So you know, obviously you're
deceiving, making it sound like you don't have it. אמר לפניו, amar
lefanav, so Moshe said to God, רבונו של עולם, Ribbono Shel Olam,
master of the universe, חמודה גנוזה יש לך, Hamudah genuzah yesh lekha,
which is the exact same thing the angels said,
this hidden treasure that you have, שאתה משתעשע בה בכל יום, She'attah
mishta'ashea bah bekhol yom, that you sort of play with it, you
indulge yourself with it, get pleasure from it every day. So again,
emphasizing this very divine nature, that it's almost like God's companion is
the Torah. So אני אחזיק טובה לעצמי, Ani ahazik tovah le-atzmi, so
I am going to, now it didn't say why would you give
it to me, he had already given it to him, but should
I sort of take credit for myself? You know, it's not because
of me that you've given me the Torah. So why should I
be the spokesperson for where the Torah is? It has nothing to
do with me. If you've given us the Torah, it is not
because we deserve it, it's because you wanted to give it. So
I'm not going to be the person to be the spokesperson for
where the Torah is. אמר לו הקדוש ברוך הוא למשה, Amar lo
Hakadosh Barukh Hu le-Moshe, so God said to Moshe, הואיל ומיעטת עצמך,
Ho'il u-mi'atat atzmekha, since you have made yourself small, you didn't want
to take credit like God gave me the Torah, תקרא על שמך,
Tikra al shimkha, it'll be called by your name, שנאמר, זכרו תורת
משה עבדי, Zikhru Torat Moshe avdi, remember the Torah of Moshe my
servant. So again, this is a little curious, I'm not exactly sure
what to do with this because first of all, you know, obviously
there's some element of if you bracket the Satan part away from
it, then it's basically saying that even when Moshe wins the argument
with the angels and gets the Torah, in the end it's underscored,
you know, that the idea again that this fundamentally is
something you know that is supernal and belongs in the heavenly realms
and that we can't take any credit for having received it and
Moshe is humble and ultimately it was God's decision to give it
to us, it wasn't like because Moshe was so brilliant we got
it, ultimately it really is God's decision, you know, it's not like
we somehow deserve it, it might be appropriate for us and so
on. So all of that I get. What I don't get is,
you know, the whole role that the Satan is playing here, you
know, that the angel,
so it's trying again like one last attempt to bring it back
up to
heaven and then I just don't get exactly, yeah I know but
again I don't get exactly what the message is. Is the Satan
supposed to be like the יצר הרע, Yetzer Hara, is the Satan
just supposed to be the thing that represents the desire to, like
the heavenly angels, desire to hold back things from human beings that
we deserve?
I mean at the end the message that Moshe is humble and
that ultimately we don't deserve it and it was God's choice to
have given it to us and the underscoring about its sort of
the nature of the Torah that even transcends that of the physical
world, all of that I get but I don't exactly get the
point about the Satan.
Yes, suggested them that, take it or leave it,
it's trying to underscore as wide as the expanse of the earth
is, as deep as the sea is, it's still not enough to
hold the Torah, right? Right. So that's what he's saying, you know,
it's even above death. It's even in a realm bigger than that.
So how can people have it? So he goes to this finite
man and if you're full of yourself, you can never have anything.
The only thing that can keep on having is when you think
you're empty. Humility, you think you have
nothing. So you can keep on absorbing more תורה if you're that
modest. Maybe that's the point.
Very nice, very nice.
He's just pointing out that man also has that nature. תורה has
a dual nature,
because first the שטן Satan sent to the earth, the physical
things. That's not where it is. That's a misunderstanding of the תורה's
just as a physical.
It has to be in the human that's the combination of the
physical and the spiritual.
Although how's resolved exactly?
Right, and how and again the role of the שטן Satan here
more than the other מלאכי השרת, specifically the שטן. Satan. But yeah,
I appreciate that, thank you. שטן Satan is the מלאך המות, Malakh
HaMaves, death is that and also has that
points out that element of the physical nature and the
material nature. Right, right, right.
Okay, so I appreciate that, thank you. And I also very much
like Mike's point. I think that the מהרש״א, Maharsha, others do make
the point that also the beginning of Mike's point, which is that
the earth and the ocean can't contain it, it's so huge. So
the idea that by משה Moshe sort of speaking about his humility
and he's nothing is what allows him to receive it. So thank
you, that's very nice. And actually, obviously that ties in to the
famous מדרש midrash about הר סיני, Har Sinai, which we're going to
discuss הר סיני, Har Sinai, but not that point about it. So
anyway, let's take a look. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Amar Rabbi
Yehoshua Ben Levi, same רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi.
said, בשעה שעלה משה למרום, Be’sha’ah she’alah Moshe l’marom when משה Moshe
went up on high, מצא להקדוש ברוך הוא שהיה קושר כתרים לאותיות.
matza l'Hakadosh Baruch Hu she-haya kosher k'tarim l'otiyot. He found God, now
you think it's going to be, but it's not. That's in מנחות.
Menachos. So we'll have to wait about five and a half years
till we get to that one. He was tying crowns on the
letters.
אמר לו משה, Amar lo Moshe, so now he asks, well let
me just say the end of this story which people are expecting
is משה Moshe says to God, why are you bothering doing that?
And God says in the end there's going to be a great
person, עקיבא בן יוסף שמו. Akiva ben Yosef shmo. He is going
to find ways to interpret things even from the little crowns on
the letters. And משה Moshe goes and he sits in the back
of the בית מדרש. beit medrash. He sits in the בית מדרש,
beit medrash, he doesn't understand what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is saying
and he keeps on getting put back and back and back in
the בית מדרש. beit medrash. And finally somebody
says, where did you get this all from? And רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva says הלכה למשה מסיני. Halakha l'Moshe mi-Sinai. So משה Moshe feels
better about that. And then משה Moshe says why are you giving
me the תורה? Give it to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Anyway, so
that's like the whole story in מנחות, Menachos, which is a very
rich אגדתא. aggadata Here we're having nothing of that. We're making almost
very little about the tying the כתרים k'tarim to the letters, which
is a central part of that story and it really just leads
us into the next discussion. But it starts with the same scene
that משה Moshe, is going up and God is tying crowns to
the letters.
אמר
לו, so God said to משה, Moshe, משה אין שלום בעירך. Moshe
ein shalom b'irkha. משה, Moshe what, in your city they don't say,
they don't say hello, they don't say שלום? shalom? You're coming there,
you're not greeting
me. אמר לפניו, so משה Moshe said to him, כלום יש עבד
שנותן שלום לרבו? klum yesh eved she-noten shalom l'rabo? Can a, is
there ever a slave that says שלום shalom to his
master? אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to him, היה לך לעזרני,
haya l'kha l'azreini, but nevertheless you should have assisted me. מיד אמר
לו, Miyad amar lo, so immediately משה Moshe said to him, ועתה
יגדל נא כח השם כאשר דברת. ve'ata yigdal na koach Hashem kaasher
dibarta.
God's power should be made great as you have spoken, God. Now
that wasn't מיד. miyad. רש״י Rashi says מיד, miyad, בעליה אחרת, b'alia
acheret, next time משה Moshe went up. So in another event, it
wasn't exactly מיד. miyad. But the גמרא Gemara here, using poetic license,
is making it as if משה responded that way. Now the point
here, it's very strange. What's the point? Why you don't say
hello? So it seems that
again, this is in a way maybe a little counterbalancing of the
previous one, because I do think it a little bit evokes that
other מדרש where רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is interpreting the כתרים, k'tarim,
which speaks very much about the human creativity in interpreting and applying
the תורה. So when משה isn't saying שלום, shalom, you say שלום
shalom to somebody, there's a sense of being sort of colleagues, which
is the whole point. How you doing, how you doing, whatever. So
משה, who am I, who am I to say שלום? shalom? I'm
here just to receive. I'm gonna stand quietly in the back, wait
till God gives me the תורה. And God is encouraging משה to
actually be more of a colleague as it was, of a participant.
So even though I'm the one tying on these letters, you should
have given me a ישר כח, yashar koach, you should have תעזרני,
tazreini, ועתה יגדל נא כח השם, ve'ata yigdal na koach Hashem, you
need to take part of the process. And so I do think
it is evoking that other מדרש about רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, which
is really the model of that human creativity in תורה שבעל פה,
Torah Shebe'al Peh, and saying that משה here wanted to maybe make
himself just a pure recipient and God is encouraging the human participation.
Okay, now we move on. ואמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Ve-amar Rabbi
Yehoshua Ben Levi, and רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi?
said, מאי דכתיב, mai d'khitiv, what is meant by the פסוק, pasuk,
וירא העם כי בשש משה, vayar ha-am ki boshesh Moshe, the people
saw that משה was hesitating. come down and then they made the
עגל, eigel, אל תקרי בשש al tikrei voshesh hesitating, אלא באו שש,
ela ba’u sheish, the sixth hour had arrived. בשעה שעלה משה למרום
when משה went up to the to the heavens to up above,
אמר להם לישראל amar lahem leYisrael he said to Israel, לסוף ארבעים
יום l’sof arba’im yom at the end of 40 days, בתחלת שש
b’tchilas sheish at the beginning of the sixth hour of the day,
אני בא, ani ba, I will return. לסוף מ' יום L’sof mem
yom at the end of 40 days, בא שטן ba Satan came
the angel and וערבב את העולם v’irvev es ha’olam and he made
the and he confused the world. אמר להם and he said to
the people, משה רבכם היכן הוא, Moshe rabchem heichan hu, where's משה
your Rebbe? אמרו לו עלו למרום, Amru lo, alu l’marom, he went
up to high. אמר להן Amar lahen he said to them, באו
שש ולא ba sheish v’lo the sixth hour has come and he
has not yet arrived, ולא השגיחו עליו v’lo hishgichu alav they didn't
pay any attention to him. מת, Meis, he's died, ולא השגיחו עליו
v’lo hishgichu alav they didn't pay any attention to him. הראה להן
דמות מטתו, Hera lahen demus mitaso, he showed them some vision of
משה’s funeral coffin, you know, in the sky or
something, והיינו דקאמרי לאהרן v’hainu deka’amri leAharon and therefore they said to
אהרן, Aharon, כי זה משה האיש, ki zeh Moshe ha’ish, this man
משה, let's say they were pointing to him because they saw the
vision of his coffin. Now, it sounds from this מדרש that part
of what allowed שטן Satan this this sort of, you know, this
entry point was that he said it's already after the hour. So
you know, right around noon time, the beginning of a sixth hour,
right, the sun is right up at the middle of the sky,
it's high, you know, it's hard to be obvious is it 11
o'clock, is it 12 o'clock, is it 1 o'clock when it's at
sort of near the apex. So that seems to be then the
וערבב את העולם, irvev es ha’olam, maybe means that he made it
cloudy, you know, so it was hard to tell exactly what time
it was. That's the way תוספות Tosafot reads it. רש"י Rashi actually
interestingly says no, that wouldn't make sense because they don't make the
עגל eigel until the next morning and משה, you know, and I
mean משה only excuse me, משה only comes down the next morning.
So it couldn't be that they were only off by an hour.
If they were only up by an hour, משה would have come
down an hour later. רש"י Rashi actually says that actually the שטן
Satan confused them not that it not that it was what time
it was in the day, but that whether again whether you count
the 40 days you include the first day or you don't include
the first day in the 40 days. But again that doesn't really
work with the emphasis of the story on the sixth hour. But
רש"י Rashi is trying to reconcile it with the פסוקים. psukim. Okay,
now we continue. אמר להו, Amar lahu,
those were the list of all the דרשות drashot from רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua בן לוי. אמר להו מרבנן לרב כהנא, Amar lahu merabbanan
leRav Kahana, one of the Rabbis said to רב כהנא, Rav Kahana,
the rabbinical students, משמיע לך מאי הר סיני? mishmi lach mai Har
Sinai? Have you heard the meaning of the words הר סיני, Har
Sinai, what the word סיני Sinai signifies? אמר ליה, Amar lei, הר
שנעשו בו נסים לישראל, Har she’nasu bo nissim leYisrael, so סיני Sinai
you read it backwards it's נס, nes, the mountain that miracles were
done to ישראל. Israel. So he says no, then הר נסאי מיבעי
ליה, Har Nissai miba’ei lei, it should have been the mountain of
miracles. אלא הר שנעשה בו סימן טוב, Ela Har she’nasu siman tov,
so סיני Sinai like סימן, siman, it was a good sign for
ישראל. Yisrael. No, הר סימנאי מיבעי ליה, Har Simannai miba’ei lei, then
it should have been הר סימנאי. Har Simannai. אמר ליה, Amar lei,
מאי טעמא לא שכיחת קמיה דרב פפא ורב הונא בריה דרב יהושע.
mai ta’ama lo shechichat kamei deRav Pappa v’Rav Huna brei deRav Yehoshua.
So you know what, maybe you should go and not not bother
me, go to רב פפא Rav Pappa and רב הונא Rav Huna
the son of רבי יהושע דמעייני באגדתא, d’ma’aini b’aggadata, they look into
אגדתא Agadata they'll give you an answer you're happy your way with.
דרב חסדא ורבה בריה דרב הונא דאמרי תרוייהו, DeRav Chisda v’Rabba brei
deRav Huna de’amri tarvaihu, and רב חסדא Rav Chisda and רבה Rabba
the son of רב הונא Rav Huna said, they both say, מאי
הר סיני, mai Har Sinai, what's הר סיני? Har Sinai? הר שירדה
שנאה לעכו"ם עליו. Har she’yardah sin’ah la’akum alav. It's the it's because
of the result of this mountain, you know, enmity from the non-Jews
came to it, that they are now jealous of us that we
have the תורה. והיינו דאמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, v’hainu d’amar Rabbi
Yose b’Rabbi Chanina, חמשה שמות יש לו, hames shemos yesh lo, there
are five names to the wilderness: מדבר צין, Midbar Tzin, now by
the way this long תוספות Tosafot points out that the גמרא’s Gemara
about to identify five things which are not clearly in the תורה
not the same location. But we're going to just bracket that, acknowledge
that that's the case, and see that for the for the purposes
here we are making all of these to say that they are
the same location. So מדבר צין, Midbar Tzin, and it's so the
the the wilderness of צין, Tzin, שנצטוו ישראל עליו, shenitztawu Yisrael alav,
so צין Tzin like ציווי, tzivui, that was where we were commanded
by the תורה. מדבר קדש, Midbar Kadesh, so קדש, Kadesh, שנתקדשו ישראל
עליו, shenitkadshu Yisrael alav, we were sanctified there by receiving the תורה.
מדבר קדמות, Midbar Kedemot, the the wilderness of of like the of
earlier of the you know of of old, שנתנה קדומה עליו, shenatnah
kedumah alav, that which preceded the world, you know, the ancient תורה
was given on it. מדבר פארן, Midbar Paran, the wilderness of פארן,
Paran, שפרו ורבו עליה, sheparu v’rabu aleha, they had you know that
they they were very fruitful on it. רש"י Rashi says if you
look at רש"י, Rashi, דכל אחד נתעברה אשתו זכר במצות שובו לכם
לאהליכם. dechol echad nit'abrah ishto zachar bemitzwat shuvu lachem l'oholeichem. So he
says when they went back to their wives, you know, after being
separate time back to the theme we started about two days ago,
they all became all their wives became pregnant and also mentioning with
male children, with that sort of a son kind that everybody wants
male children. And then רש"י Rashi says ולא ידענא היכא רמיזא. v’lo
yadana heicha remizah. I don’t know where this idea is hinted to,
but clearly this גמרא Gemara is assuming it that that that that
happened after they after they got back together after הר סיני. Har
Sinai. And מדבר, Midbar, that's number four, and מדבר סיני, Midbar Sinai,
so here talking about מדבר Midbar as opposed to the הר סיני,
Har Sinai, but the same point, שירדה שנאה לעכו"ם עליו. she'yarda sina
l'akum alav. That's where the hatred or jealousy comes because we have
the תורה. ומה שמו, u'mah shemo, so what is the actual name
of the mountain? חורב שמו, Chorev shemo, the name is חורב. Chorev.
ופליגא דרבי אבהו, u'pliga d'Rabbi Abbahu, and it argues on רבי אבהו
Rabbi Abbahu דאמר רבי אבהו d'amar Rabbi Abbahu הר סיני שמו, Har
Sinai shemo, no, its proper name is הר סיני, Har Sinai, so
we can't make drashas, whatever it is, that's the name. למה נקרא
הר חורב, lamah nikra Har Chorev, the thing that's more descriptive rather
than the proper name is הר חורב. Har Chorev. Why is it
called הר חורב? Har Chorev? שירדה חורבה לעכו"ם עליו she'yarda churva l'akum
alav because there sort of desolation comes to the non-Jews on it
again because we have the תורה, so ultimately it's good for us
and bad for them. So that's obviously introducing this whole other theme
that had been absent here but is present in other גמראs Gemara
about the non-Jews having been given a choice. There's a גמרא Gemara
in עבודה זרה Avoda Zara where God actually takes the non-Jews to
task at the time of ימות המשיח y'mot ha'Mashiach and says why
did you not do מצוות, mitzvot the מצוות you were commanded, and
they say hey you never gave us the תורה, you can't blame
us for not having had the opportunity. So this whole question about
how this impacts on our relationship to the non-Jews is a theme
that occurs in many different contexts, here's just sort of alluded to
a little bit. Yes, רבקה.
Can I go back to
השטן ha'Satan and point out from רבי יהושע בן לוי?
השטן ha'Satan seems to go up and
down.
That's a good point, and then he comes down to trick them
about משה's death, right?
Is he depicted as
independent from God?
Right. That's a good... the whole role of השטן, ha'Satan, I mean
that's a much larger discussion. In the
תורה, you don't have השטן, ha'Satan, you have the angel going by
בלעם Bilaam לשטן לו, l'Satan lo, שטן Satan is a verb. The
first השטן ha'Satan appears as an independent is in איוב Iyov where
השטן ha'Satan comes before God and says
basically is sort of
a troublemaker and gets God to agree to do
this. But in nowhere in תנ"ך Tanakh or in the גמרא Gemara
does שטן Satan have any power outside of God. Ultimately there's no
question of a challenge of God's ultimate power and authority, and in
that way it's different
than in Christian theology and so on which really sees השטן ha'Satan
as threatening
God's control. But does השטן, ha'Satan, is השטן, ha'Satan, let's put it
this way, empowered by God to sort of play this role, play
the devil's advocate, play the
devil? But that's the idea when you say I want to play
the devil's advocate, it means that ultimately there's a function in somebody
representing this other side. That seems to be the idea, and that
it is given a certain amount of control or of freedom to
play that role. So yes.
רש"י Rashi just says it's הוא יצר הרע. hu yeitzer hara.
Right, so that's another question. There's a גמרא Gemara that says השטן
הוא יצר הרע, ha'Satan hu yeitzer hara, right? But then it talks...
that's something inside of us. But that's the way we would read
it, some people would read יצר הרע yeitzer hara really do sort
of imagine יצר הרע yeitzer hara as this
external. But you're right, there are those approaches that read, right, and
the רש"י Rashi here does quote that, that read that very much.
But it doesn't exactly fit the earlier גמרא, Gemara, the השטן ha'Satan
in... yeah, right. Anyway, I don't want to get into
it. But yeah, there are those questions about how much to see
השטן ha'Satan as an independent entity. All right, now we find... that
is the end of our discussion about מתן תורה Matan Torah. which
was a great opportunity
based on this whole discussion about פליטת שכבת זרע pleitat shichvat zera
and learning things from פסוקים. We had this wonderful discussion about מתן
תורה. Now we get back to the משנה, Mishna, and the other
thing the משנה Mishna asked was about the red strand on the
horns of the goat of the שעיר המשתלח. se'ir ha'mishtaleiach. Where do
you know this from? And it quotes the פסוק pasuk אם יהיו
חטאיכם כשנים כשלג ילבינו, im yihyu chata'eichem kashanim kasheleg yalbinu, which never
exactly says that that's what we're supposed to do is tie a
red strand, but somehow that's what we base it on. So let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
כשנים, kashanim, like red, כשני מבעי ליה, kashani mibaei lei, like a
red strand, a crimson. כשלג ילבינו, kasheleg yalbinu, so it doesn't say
כשלגים. kashlagim. So why does it say אם יהיו חטאיכם כשנים כשלג?
im yihyu chata'eichem kashanim kasheleg? It should be the כשנים כשלגים kashanim
kashlagim or כשני כשלג. kashani kasheleg. So אמר רבי יצחק, amar Rabbi
Yitzchak, אמר להם הקדוש ברוך הוא לישראל, amar lahem ha'Kadosh Baruch Hu
l'Yisrael, God said to ישראל, Yisrael, so we're still, even though we're
in the next part of the משנה, Mishna, we're going to be
אגדתא agadata all straight to the next משנה. Mishna. So anyway, so
God said to ישראל, Yisrael, אם יהיו חטאיכם כשנים הללו, im yihyu
chata'eichem kashanim halalu, even if your sins were as long-standing as all
the years מששת ימי בראשית, mi'sheishet y'mei Bereishit, even if you've been
sinning from the beginning of creation, which we haven't, so nevertheless ועד
עכשיו, v'ad achshav, until now, כשלג ילבינו kasheleg yalbinu I will whiten
them. Okay, so it's not just if they're red, but you know
if they're sort of like very deep and bad, but also if
they're very ongoing. Right. Okay,
דרש רבא, darash Rava, so Rava interpreted, מאי דכתיב, mai d'ichtiv, what's
meant by the פסוק pasuk לכו נא ונוכחה יאמר ה'. l'chu na
v'nivacha yomar Hashem. come now and let us sort of debate or
remonstrate you says God, אם יהיו חטאיכם כשני כשלג ילבינו, im yihyu
chata'echem kashanim kasheleg yalbinu, right, so you're going to sort of stand
to judgment but I would cleanse you, I would cleanse your sins.
So לכו נא, lechu na, go now, בא נא מיבעי ליה, bo
na miba'ei lei, it should have meant come now and let us
sort of argue and I'll remonstrate.
So יאמר ה', yomar Hashem, God will say, אמר ה' מיבעי ליה,
amar Hashem miba'ei lei, it should have said, so בא נא מיבעי
ליה, bo na miba'ei lei, it should have said come now, and
יאמר ה' אמר ה' מיבעי ליה, yomar Hashem amar Hashem miba'ei lei,
God had said, not will say. So here's how we're going to
read what happened in this little exchange. לעתיד לבוא, le'atid lavo, in
the future, when you know the end of days, when we have
to come and stand judgment, יאמר להם הקדוש ברוך הוא לישראל, yomar
lahem Hakadosh Baruch Hu leYisrael, God will say to ישראל, Israel, לכו
נא, lechu na, go, not come to me and let us debate,
but go, you go, אצל אבותיכם, etzel avoteichem, to your forefathers, ויוכיחו
אתכם, veyochi'chu etchem, and they'll remonstrate you for your evil deeds. So
God was deputizing that function.
So ויוכיחו אתכם, veyochi'chu etchem, ויאמרו לפניו, veyomru lefanav, and then בני
ישראל Bnei Yisrael will say to God, רבונו של עולם, Ribbono Shel
Olam, Master of the Universe, אצל מי נלך, etzel mi nelech, who
should we go to? אצל אברהם, etzel Avraham, you want us to
go to אברהם? Avraham, שאמרת לו, she'amarta lo, you said to אברהם,
Avraham ידוע תדע, yado'a teda, you should know that your children, your
seed will be a stranger in a foreign land for 400 years,
ולא ביקש רחמים עלינו, velo bikeish rachamim aleinu, and he didn't try
to defend us, so he's not the person we want to get
מוסר musar from, he didn't try to defend us
when you told him about this punishment, about whatever, about the exile.
So אצל יצחק, etzel Yitzchak, maybe you think we should go to
יצחק? Yitzchak שבירך את עשו והיה כאשר תריד, shebeirach et Eisav vehayah
ka'asher tarid, ולא ביקש רחמים עלינו, velo bikeish rachamim aleinu, that he
said to עשו Eisav it will be when you know when they
subjugate you that then ופרקת עלו מעל צוארך, ufarakta ulo mei'al tzavvarecha,
that you'll cast off their yoke. So you know יצחק Yitzchak, was
okay with עשו Eisav ultimately having dominion over us at certain times,
so he's not the one we want to get compassion for, we
can expect compassion from. אצל יעקב, etzel Yaakov, maybe we should go
to יעקב? Yaakov שאמרת לו אנכי ארד עמך מצרימה ואנכי אעלך גם
עלה, she'amarta lo Anochi eireid imcha Mitzrayma veAnochi a'alcha gam alo, I
will go down with you and come up with you, meaning that
you're going to be down in מצרים Mitzrayim. for a long time,
ולא ביקש רחמים עלינו, velo bikeish rachamim aleinu, and he didn't ask
for compassion to try to protect us from the exile.
So we can't trust our forefathers, yeah they were great, but we're
afraid they won't be compassionate enough, they'll seek out too much of
a מדת הדין.
middat hadin. Oh he's saying that who are they to rebuke? We
have a טענה ta'ana against them.
No, I don't think so. I don't think so. It's about רחמים,
rachamim, they're not going to have enough compassion in the process. So
אצל מי נלך, etzel mi nelech, who should we go to? עכשיו
יאמר ה', achshav yomar Hashem, You God, You be the one to
give us מוסר, musar, we'll put our trust in You. אמר להם
הקדוש ברוך הוא, amar lahem Hakadosh Baruch Hu, so God said, הואיל
ותליתם עצמכם בי, ho'il utelitem atzmechem bi, since you were willing to
trust Me to be your judge and you didn't want to go
to anyone else, then you know what? אם יהיו חטאיכם כשני כשלג
ילבינו, im yihyu chata'echem kashanim kasheleg yalbinu, then I will have compassion
on you, I will cleanse you of your sins. So again, I
don't know, it's a nice little דרש drash on the פסוק, pasuk,
I'm not exactly sure again like the larger message here, casts אברהם
יצחק ויעקב Avraham Yitzchak veYaakov who normally are cast in very sympathetic
lights to in this very negative, but maybe to some degree what
it is is it's more of a message about
תשובה, that we more have to give our sort of really really
give ourselves over to God's
judgment and
in that sort of process of תשובה. But anyway, I don't know
sort of more what to make from this. You know what תחנון
Tachanun that David says that about. Yeah that's a good point, נפלה
נא ביד ה', nepla na beyad Hashem, excellent point. Right we say
that in תחנון, Tachanun, right. So maybe sometimes we expect, you know
God is often if anything okay it makes אברהם יצחק ויעקב Avraham
Yitzchak veYaakov look bad but it makes God look good. Often God
is like מדת הדין middat hadin and He's going to take us
to judgment and we can more hope like people will be nicer
to us and here it's really saying no ultimately the true judgment
and the judgment with compassion is to apprehend yourself over to God.
Okay so now continues, אמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן,
Amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan, מאי דכתיב, mai dechtiv,
what's meant by the verse, כי אתה אבינו, Ki Atah Avinu, You
God are our Father, כי אברהם לא ידענו וישראל לא יכירנו, ki
Avraham lo yedanu veYisrael lo yakiranu, Avraham doesn't know us, Israel does
not recognize us, אתה ה' אבינו גאלנו מעולם שמך, Atah Hashem Avinu
go'aleinu mei'olam shemecha, You are Hashem our Father, our Redeemer, from eternity
is Your name. So here clearly the same type of a theme
that we put our faith ultimately in You and not in אברהם
יצחק ויעקב. Avraham Yitzchak veYaakov. So לעתיד לבוא יאמר להם הקדוש ברוך
הוא לאברהם, le'atid lavo yomar lahem Hakadosh Baruch Hu leAvraham, so in
the future time and now this story is like the real sort
of parallel of the previous one because we will see how אברהם
יצחק ויעקב Avraham Yitzchak veYaakov are going to deal with the fact
that we have sinned. In the future God will say
to
אברהם, בניך חטאו, banecha chatu, your children have sinned to Me. אמר
לפניו, so אברהם will say
before Him, רבונו של עולם Ribbono Shel Olam Master of the
Universe. maybe I'll you know what maybe I'll tell יעקב Yaakov *Yaakov*
דהוה ליה צער גידול בנים tza'ar gidul banim *d'hava lei tza'ar gidul
banim* he really suffered raising kids. I mean אברהם *Avraham* had his
issues with יצחק *Yitzchak* and ישמעאל *Yishmael* מוסיף על זה *mosif al
ze* you don't see אברהם *Avraham* getting too involved seems like שרה
*Sarah* was a lot sort of dealing with those issues but יעקב
Yaakov *Yaakov* he really suffered with raising the kids he'll have compassion
on you know on you know on the kids אפשר דבעי רחמי
עליי *efshar d'ba'ei rachamei alai* maybe he'll ask for compassion. אמר ליה
*Amar lei* so God said to יעקב Yaakov *Yaakov* בניך חטאו *banecha
chatu* your children have sinned. אמר לפניו *Amar lefanav* יעקב Yaakov. *Yaakov*
said ריבונו של עולם *Ribono shel Olam* Master of the universe ימחו
על קדושת שמך *yimachu al kdushat shemecha* let them be wiped out
for your holy name if they sinned against you get the punishment
they deserve. אמר *Amar* so God said לא בסבי טעמא ולא בדרדקי
עצה *lo b'savei ta'ama v'lo b'dardakei eitza* not in elders is there
sense and not in the youth is there is there like wisdom
is there is there you know is there advice. So I can't
trust אברהם *Avraham* he's too old I can't trust יעקב *Yaakov* he's
too young you know what I'll go to יצחק *Yitzchak*. אמר ליה
ליצחק *Amar lei l'Yitzchak* so God said to יצחק *Yitzchak* בניך חטאו
לי *banecha chatu li* your children have sinned to me. אמר לפניו
*Amar lefanav* so יצחק *Yitzchak* said to him said in front of
him ריבונו של עולם *Ribono shel Olam* Master of the universe בני
*banai* my children? ולא בניך *v'lo banecha* and not your children? בשעה
שהקדימו לפניך *B'shaa she'hikdimu lefanav* נעשה לנשמע *na'aseh l'nishmah* when they said
to the nice tie in to the beginning to the earlier sort
of מדרשים *midrashim* when they said נעשה *na'aseh* before נשמע *nishmah* קראת
להם *karata lahem* you called them בני בכורי ישראל *beni bechori Yisrael*.
Now actually בני בכורי *beni bechori* appears in the narrative much before
נעשה ונשמע *na'aseh v'nishmah* but the point is when they're doing what
you like then you're totally happy to call them your children my
child my my children my firstborn. עכשיו *Achshav* now that they're sinning
בני *banai* my children? ולא בניך *v'lo banecha* and not your children?
ועוד *V'od* let's figure out how much they actually sinned before you.
All right כמה שנותיו של אדם *kama shnotav shel adam* שבעים שנה
*shiv'im shana* how long is an average lifespan of a person 70
years. דל עשרין דלא ענשת עלייהו *dal esrin d'lo anashta aleihu* take
away 20 years that the first 20 years you know is considered
that they're not yet deserving of punishment. We say בר מצוה *Bar
Mitzvah* but that's sort of for a punishment in the in the
sort of earthly court. There's a sense that a person is not
deserving of a punishment from God until they're 20 years old. Let's
take away the first 20 years they're not deserving of punishment. פשו
להו חמשים *pashu lehu chamishim* we're left with 50 years. דל כ"ה
דלילותא *dal chamesh v'esrin d'leiluta* take off 25 years that's nighttime so
they're sleeping. I don't know you gotta sleep a lot 12 hours
maybe okay maybe the point is that you're at least at home
at night so how much opportunity is there to sin when you're
when you're at home? So you take off that 25 now we're
left with only 25 years. Okay פשו להו כ"ה *pashu lehu chamesh
v'esrin* we're left with 25 years. דל תרתי סרי ופלגא *dal tartei
srei u'palga* take off 12 and a half cut it in half
דצלויי ומאכל ודבית הכסא *d'tzalu'ei u'meichal u'd'veit hakisei* cause you know so
take away the time that we're דאוונינג *davening* and eating and going
to the bathroom so off half of our time. So we're left
with 12 and a half 12 and a half years. פשו להו
תרתי סרי ופלגא *pashu lehu tartei srei u'palga* you're left with 12
and a half. אם אתה סובל את כולם *im ata sovel et
kulam* מוטב *mutav* so 12 and a half years the most they
could have sinned was 12 and a half years' worth. Okay if
you want to take the burden of all of those sins that's
the best. ואם לאו *v'im lav* and if you're not willing to
to sort of take the full burden of that פלגא עליי ופלגא
עליך *palga alai u'palga alecha* we'll split it I'll take half the
responsibility you'll take the other half and we can be מוחל *mocheil*
it. ואם תמצא לומר כולם עליי *v'im timtza lomar kulam alai* and
if you want to say it's all my responsibility I need to
take all of that sort of you know sort of you know
sort of responsibility for their sin so you know what fine הא
קריבית נפשי קמך *ha karivti nafshi kamach* I offered up my entire
soul to you so even if I somehow take all that responsibility
they should be atoned for because I was willing to give my
entire person over to you at at the עקידה *Akeidah*. So פתחו
ואמרו *patchu v'amru* so then when after יצחק *Yitzchak* said that they
opened up and they said כי אתה אבינו *ki ata avinu*. Now
notice אתה *ata* is not God right כי אתה אבינו כי אברהם
לא ידענו וישראל לא יכירנו *ki ata avinu ki Avraham lo yedanu
v'Yisrael lo yakirenu* it didn't mention יצחק *Yitzchak* in that פסוק *pasuk*.
So they said ah you you're our true father יצחק *Yitzchak* you
were willing to take the responsibility. אמר להם יצחק *Amar lahem Yitzchak*
יצחק *Yitzchak* said עד שאתם מקלסין לי *ad she'atem me'kalsin li* you're
praising me קלסו להקדוש ברוך הוא *kalsu l'Hakadosh Baruch Hu* so you
should be praising God ומחוי להו יצחק להקדוש ברוך הוא בעינייהו *u'machvei
lehu Yitzchak l'Hakadosh Baruch Hu b'eineihu*. So God so he sort of
like you know like indicated with his eyes he looked over to
God says don't talk to me you know you should be directing
your praise to God. מיד *Miyad* נשאו עיניהם למרום *nas'u eineihem l'marom*
so then they all looked up to heaven ואומרים *v'omrim* כי אתה
השם אבינו גואלנו מעולם שמך *ki ata Hashem avinu go'aleinu me'olam shemecha*
you השם *Hashem* are our father. So treating the פסוק *pasuk* you
יצחק *Yitzchak* are our father because אברהם *Avraham* and ישראל *Yisrael* did
us no good and then יצחק *Yitzchak* says don't talk to me
talk to God and then the end of the פסוק *pasuk* is
כי אתה השם אבינו *ki ata Hashem avinu* you are השם *Hashem*
our our God. So yes it is very interesting I don't really
know what to make about this whole you know story. I mean
obviously it's nice in that it sort of shows you know downplaying
how bad could we have really sinned and you know the idea
that that you know that there are those that will defend us
for our sin and so on but You know, again, the whole
question about making אברהם and יעקב look bad and how that plays
out with זכות אבות. Zechut Avot. So the only person that's really
willing to defend us is יצחק, and you know, it was very
powerful the idea of יעקב with the צער גידול בנים and then
to cast him as somebody after having suffered all of that, you
know, to uncaring about the fate of the children
is, you know, again, I really don't know what to sort of
more broadly what to make out of these מדרשים. Let's just finish
to the end of the
משנה. mishna. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi
Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, ראוי היה יעקב אבינו לירד למצרים
בשלשלאות של ברזל. ra'uy hayah Yaakov Avinu leredet l'Mitzrayim b'shalshela'ot shel barzel.
Since it was decreed because we had mentioned obviously before, you know,
גר יהיה זרעך, ger yiheyeh zar'acha, and you'll be taken down and
there'll be you know, strangers in a strange land, so you know,
presumably that would have meant that he would have been like taken
down in chains of iron, like you know, taken as a slave
brought down to מצרים. Mitzrayim. אלא שזכותו גרמה לו. Ella she'zchuto garmah
lo. His merit you know, allowed it to become you know in
a much nicer way. דכתיב, D'chtiv, בחבלי אדם אמשכם בעבותות אהבה. b'chevlei
adam emshachem b'avotot ahavah. I will in the in the ropes of
people I will draw them in the with bonds of love. ואהיה
להם כמרימי עול על לחיהם. Va'ehyeh lahem k'merimei ol al lecheyeihem. I
will be like one that lifts up the burden, you know, by
their you know, by their jaw. ואט
אליו אוכיל. V'at elav ochil. And I will, you know, I I
you know, I will I will incline towards them so that they
can so that they can bear the burden. So God made it
easy, you know, which we just read in the פרשה parsha of
יעקב to coming down to מצרים. So maybe here it's a little
bit coming a little to defend יעקב after he said all these
bad things, you know, that whatever that יעקב merited at least this.
So obviously, you know, shouldn't end with a bad message about יעקב.
Let's try we have three more minutes, so let's get to the
bottom of the דף. Now we already put all this end with
this אגדתא and now get back to the business of how big
do things have to be in order to be חייב chayav for
carrying them on שבת. The business we've been in for the last,
I don't know, three weeks. So anyway, המוציא עצים, hamotzi etzim, if
you take out wood, כדי לבשל ביצה קלה. k'dei l'vashel beitzah kalah.
Enough wood to cook a light egg, which we said before meant
like a hen's egg and to fry it with oil and not
even the size of an egg, just the size of a of
a you know, of a fig. All right, תבלין, tavlin, how about
spices? How much is significant? כדי לתבל ביצה קלה, k'dei l'tabel beitzah
kalah, the amount of spices you would add to give to put
spices on this egg, which is a very small amount, a little
salt, a little pepper. ומצטרפין זה עם זה, U'mitztarfin zeh im zeh,
they would combine. So if you have a little salt and a
little pepper and each one is not enough by itself, but combine,
that then then that they would combine. קליפי אגוזים, kliphei egozim, קליפי
רמונים, kliphei rimonim, איסטיס ופואה, istis v'puah, all these different types of
shells of nuts and of pomegranates and איסטיס ופואה istis v'puah which
are two other types of plants, all things that are used to
make dyes. כדי לצבוע בהם בגד קטן פי שבכה, k'dei litzboa bahem
beged katan pi sevechah, in order to use to make the dye
of a small garment that would be on the top on the
opening of a hairnet. מי רגלים, Mei raglayim, how about urine? נתר
ובורית, neter u'vorit, קמוליא ואשלג, kamulya va'ashlag, and all of those were
different cleansing agents. So כדי לכבס בגד קטן פי שבכה, k'dei lachabbes
beged katan pi sevechah, that's the amount of cleansing agents that would
require to cleanse a small garment that would fit on the opening
of a hairnet. רבי יהודה אומר כדי להעביר את הכתם, Rabbi Yehuda
omer k'dei l'ha'avir et haketem, to remove a stain that a woman
would have from menstrual staining. So not the ent—not clear whether that's
smaller or bigger. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: תנינא חדא זימנא.
Tanina chada zimna. We already taught once this idea about how much
wood is a minimum amount. קנה, kaneh, a reed, כדי לעשות קולמוס,
k'dei la'asot kulmos, the size to make a a quill. אם היה
עב או מרוסס, im hayah av o merusas, if it was thick
or if it was broken, so you couldn't make a quill out
of it, כדי לבשל ביצה קלה שבביצים, k'dei l'vashel beitzah kalah shebe'beitzim,
in order to cook the lightest egg, again meaning a hen's egg,
ונתונה באילפס טרופה, u'netunah b'ilfas truphah, sort of scrambled, ונתונה באילפס, u'netunah
b'ilfas, in a frying pan. So anyway, there you have it. מהו
דתימא, Mah d'teima, I might have thought, התם הוא דלא חזי למידי,
hatham hu d'lo chazi l'midi, that's because if you have a shattered
reed, you can't use it for anything. So the only thing you
can measure it by is firewood. אבל עצים דחזו לקחדא דאקלידא, aval
etzim d'chazu l'kachadda d'aklida, but but woods that could be maybe used
as a tooth in a in a key, so אפילו כל שהוא,
afilu kol shehu, even a small amount of wood, maybe you could
use it for some other function. קמשמע לן, Kamashma lan, that that's
not a standard use, a standard use for wood is firewood, and
you measure it by firewood.